<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>lvh (python)</title><link>http://www.lvh.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.lvh.io/categories/python.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2015 22:10:17 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>On discussing software security improvements</title><link>http://www.lvh.io/posts/on-discussing-software-security-improvements.html</link><dc:creator>lvh</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A common criticism of information security folks is that they tend to
advise people to not do any crypto. Through projects like &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.crypto101.io/"&gt;Crypto
101&lt;/a&gt;, I've attempted to make a small contribution towards fixing
that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the open source world, various people often try to improve the
security of a project. Because designing secure systems is pretty
hard, they often produce flawed proposals. The aforemetioned tendency
for infosec-conscious people to tell them to stop doing crypto is
experienced as unwelcoming, even dismissive. Typically, the only thing
that's accomplished is that a lot of feelings get hurt; it seems to
only rarely result in improved software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that's quite unfortunate. I think open source is great, and we
should be not just welcoming and inclusive, but aiming to produce
secure software. Furthermore, even if a flawed proposal is
unsalvageable, a clear description of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it is flawed will
presumably result in fewer negative interactions. Best case scenario,
the issues with a proposal can be discussed and potentially rectified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an effort to improve this situation, I'm documenting what I believe
to be a useful way to discuss security changes and their tradeoffs. As
Zooko has taught me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Security isn't about perfect versus imperfect or about better versus
worse, it's about &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; attack surface versus &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; attack
surface.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This document aims to be the equivalent of an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sscce.org/"&gt;SSCCE&lt;/a&gt; for generic bug
reports: a blueprint for making suggestions likely to lead to
productive discourse, as long as we can agree that we're trying to
produce more secure software, as well as provide a welcoming
development environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="important-points"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Important points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good proposal should contain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A brief description of what you're suggesting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A description of the attack model you're considering, why the
current system does not address this issue, and why the suggested
system &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; address this issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A motivation of the attack model. Why is it important that this
issue is actually addressed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does this change affect the attack surface (i.e. all of the
ways an attacker can attempt to attack a system)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What does the user experience for all users of the system look
like? Many cryptosystems fall over because they're simply unusable
for most users of the system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="an-example"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;An example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wul (the widely underestimated language, pronounced &lt;em&gt;/wool/&lt;/em&gt;) is a
general purpose programming language. It has a package repository,
WuPI (the Wul package index, pronounced &lt;em&gt;/woopie/&lt;/em&gt;), the de facto
standard for distributing and installing Wul software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WuPI uses TLS as a secure transport. The WuF (Wul foundation,
pronounced &lt;em&gt;/woof/&lt;/em&gt;), maintains a root certificate, distributed with
Wul. Thanks to a well-managed system of intermediary CAs run by a
tireless army of volunteers, this means that both package authors and
consumers know they're talking to the real WuPI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alice is the WuPI BDFL. Bob is a Wul programmer, and would like to
improve the security of WuPI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While consumers and authors know that they're talking to the real
WuPI, there is no protection against a malicious WuPI endpoint. (This
problem was recently made worse because WuPI introduced a CDN, greatly
increasing the number of people who could own a node.). You know that
you're talking to something with a WuF-signed certificate (presumably
WuPI, provided the WuF has done a good job managing that certificate),
but you have no idea if that thing is being honest about the packages
it serves you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bob believes WuPI could solve this by using GPG signatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He starts with a brief description of the suggestion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I would like to suggest that WuPI grows support for GPG signatures
of packages. These signatures would be created when a package author
uploads a package. They would optionally be verified when the user
downloads a package.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He continues with the attack model being considered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I believe this would secure WuPI consumers against a malicious WuPI
endpoints. A malicious WuPI endpoint (assuming it acquires an
appropriate certificate) is currently free to deliver whatever
packages it wants.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He explains why the current model doesn't address this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The current system assures authenticity and secrecy of the stream
(through TLS), and it ensures that the server authenticates itself
with a WuPI/WuF certificate. It does not ensure that the package is
what the author uploaded.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He explains why he believes his model does address this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Because the signatures are produced by the author's GPG key, a
malicious WuPI endpoint would not be able to forge them. Therefore,
a consumer is sure that a package with a valid signature is indeed
from the author.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He explains why this attack model is important:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
With the new CDN support, the number of people with access to such a
certificate has greatly increased. While I certainly trust all of
the volunteers involved, it would be nice if we didn't &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to.
Furthermore, the software on the servers can always be vulnerable to
attack; as a high-value target, it certainly isn't inconceivable
that an attacker would use an unknown vulnerability to take over a
WuPI endpoint.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He (believes to) address the attack surface:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Because the signatures are optional, the attack surface remains the
same.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, he addresses the user experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weak point of this scheme is most likely the user experience,
because users historically seem to dislike using GPG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am hopeful that this increased value of participating in the GPG
web of trust will mean that more people participate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alice reviews this, and notes a flaw in the proposal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
This proposal aims to address a security flaw when the WuPI endpoint
is malicious by adding signatures. However, a malicious WuPI
endpoint can lie by omission, and claim a package was never signed
by the author.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bob now realizes this issue, and suggests an improvement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
This could be rectified if the user insists on a signature for
packages they expect to be signed.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a side note, Alice notes that the attack surface does increase:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
This places trust in author's ability to manage private keys, which
has historically been shown to be problematic. That introduces a new
attack vector: an attacker can attempt to go after the author's
private key.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the outcome of this conversation, there actually was a
conversation. I believe this to be an improvement over the overall
status quo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>crypto</category><category>python</category><category>security</category><guid>http://www.lvh.io/posts/on-discussing-software-security-improvements.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2014 06:58:27 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>